Register of the William H. Vatcher Papers, 1939-1965
Hoover Institution Archives
William H. Vatcher Papers,
1939-1965
53006
Vatcher, William Henry
18 manuscript boxes, 4 envelopes 7.9 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, writings, pamphlets, leaflets, slides, and photographs, relating to South African political parties; Afrikaner and African nationalism; the Afrikaner Broederbond; American, Japanese, and North Korean propaganda and psychological warfare methods during World War II and the Korean War; and the Trans-Siberian Railroad
Administrative Information
Access
Collection open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1953.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Access Points
Afrikaner Broederbond; Trans-Siberian Railroad; Korean War, 1950-1953; Korean War, 1950-1953--Propaganda; Korean War, 1950-1953--Psychological aspects; Nationalism--South Africa; Propaganda, American; Propaganda, Japanese; Propaganda, Korean; Railroads--Soviet Union; Psychological warfare; World War, 1939-1945; World War, 1939-1945--Propaganda; World War, 1939-1945--Psychological aspects; Africa; Japan; Korea; South Africa; South Africa--Politics and government; South Africa--Race relations; Soviet Union; Russia (Federation); United States--Foreign relations; Slides (Photography)
Biographical Note
William Henry Vatcher
1920, July Born, Los Angeles, California
1942 B.A., Stanford University
1944-1945 Member, Admiral Nimitz's Staff, Central Pacific
1945-1946 Member, Naval Technical Mission to Japan
1948 M.A., Stanford University
1950 Ph.D., Stanford University
1950 Author, Combat Propaganda Against the Japanese in the Central Pacific
1949-1951 Instructor, San Jose State College, San Jose, California
1951 Member, Panmunjom Truce Team, Korea
1958 Author, Panmunjom: the Story of the Korean Military Armistice
1965 Author, White Laager: the Rise of Afrikaner Nationalism
Series Description
- Correspondence, 1952-1964. (Box Box No. 1)
  Arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent.
- Subject File, 1939-1965. (Box Box No. 1-16)
  Reports, memoranda, printed material, arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
- Speeches and Writings, 1949-1962. (Box Box No. 16-17)
  Notes, drafts, printed copies of writings, arranged alphabetically by title or subject.
- Miscellany. (Box Box No. 17)
  Campaign buttons of John F. Kennedy, Senate souvenir pen.
- Audio-Visual.
  See photo card catalog for photographs, cartoons, and slides.
Container List
- Correspondence, 1952-1964
  - General, 1960 (Box 1.)
  - Unidentified, 1952-1955
  - Barclay, Thomas S., 1961
  - Basson, Jackie, 1961
  - Brandt, Willy, 1960
  - Brown, Edmund G., Sr., 1957
  - Byrne, Lional, 1955
  - Crowe, Philip K., 1961
  - Curray, James, 1961
  - Davis, S., 1961
  - De Villiers, Rene M., 1961-1963
  - Dlamini, Clement, 1961
  - Dobkins, Maurice, 1961-1963
  - Ekonomiese Institut, 1961
  - Elliott, Harold W., 1962
  - Eustace, P. J., 1961-1964
  - Fagan, H. A., 1960
  - Goldberg, A., 1961
  - Grant, W., 1961
  - Jablonski, Ann F., 1961
  - Jackson, Henry M., 1960
  - Joy, Admiral C. Turner, 1955
  - Kefauver, Estes, 1959
  - Kennedy, Edward, 1963
  - Kennedy, President John F., 1957-1961
  - Mbelu, Francis, 1961
  - Mphahtele, Armstrong, n.d.
  - Munro, Sterling S., 1960
  - Nugent, D. R., 1954
  - Parkington, M. W., 1961
  - Salisbury, O. J., 1961
  - Sargeant, Geoff, 1955
  - Sattar, Abdul, 1960-1962
  - Saund, D. S., 1960
  - Smith, Stephen E., 1959
  - Steyn, S. J. M., 1961
  - Terry, Godfrey A., 1961
  - United Party, 1961
  - Vatcher, Mr. and Mrs. William H., Sr., 1952
  - Viljoen, D. T., 1961-1962
  - Winter, William, 1952
- Subject File, 1939-1965
  - Africa, South (Box 1.)
    - General
      - Map
      - Miscellany
      - Notes by W. H. Vatcher
      - Songbooks (Box 2.)
    - African National Congress
    - African Student Union
    - Apartheid
    - Botha, P. W.
    - Constitution
    - Description and travel - 1951-1965
    - Division of Information and Research
    - Doenges, T. E.
    - Economy
    - Education
    - Federasie van Afrikaanse Kultuurvereniginge (Federation of African Cultural Associations)
    - Forman, Lionel
    - Forssman, Magnus J. F.
    - Fox, Melvin J.
    - Hertzog, Gen. J. B. M.
    - Immigration
    - Kruger, President Jannie (Box 3.)
    - Labor
    - National Union of South African Students
    - National Youth Organization
    - Political parties
      - Communist Party
      - Dominion Party
      - Federal Party
      - Miscellany (Box 4.)
      - National Party
      - Progressive Party
      - South African Bond
      - South African Congress of Democrats
      - South African Labour Party
      - South-West Party
      - Union Party (Box 5.)
    - Race relations
    - Schoeman, Johan
    - South Africa Foundation
    - South African Congress of Trade Unions
    - South African Indian Congress (Box 6.)
    - South West Africa
    - Treason Trial, 1957-1961
    - United Nations
  - Biographical material
  - Congo
  - Japanese language - Study and teaching
    - Notebooks
    - Notebooks (Box 7.)
    - Notes by W. H. Vatcher, study guides, worksheets (Box 8.)
    - Notes by W. H. Vatcher, study guides, worksheets (Box 9.)
    - Texts and workbooks
    - Texts and workbooks (Box 10.)
    - Texts and workbooks (Box 11.)
  - Korean War, 1950-1953
    - General
      - Memoranda
      - Notes by W. H. Vatcher
      - Printed material
    - Propaganda, American (Box 12.)
      - Chinese in North Korea
      - North Korean Army and civilians (Box 13.)
      - North Korean Army and civilians (Box 14.)
    - Propaganda, North Korean
      - North Korean Army
      - South Korean Army
      - United Nations Forces
      - United States Army
  - Miscellany
  - United States - Army General School
  - World War, 1939-1945 (Box 15.)
    - Propaganda, American
      - General
      - China
      - Japanese Forces
      - Japanese Forces (Box 16.)
      - Miscellany
    - Propaganda, Japanese
      - American Forces. Includes Douglas MacArthur letter.
- Speeches and Writings, 1949-1962
  - Class outline and notes (Box 16.)
  - Combat Propaganda: Guadalcanal, Marshalls, Marianas, Carolines, Iwo Jima,1949, draft of dissertation, 1 typewritten copy.
  - Miscellaneous notes (Box 17.)
  - Nationalist Struggle for Power in South Africa, n.d., 1 photocopy.
  - Siberian Sketchbook, 1962, 1 typewritten copy.
  - South Africa and the United States, n.d., 1 typewritten draft.
  - Squawk Boxes and Paper Bombs, n.d., 1 typewritten draft.
- Miscellany.
  - Campaign buttons, souvenir pen (John F. Kennedy) (Box 17.)
- Audio-Visual. See photo card catalog for photographs, cartoons, and slides.